welcome to the fourth active inference
Symposium Dr gomo
rostini we're very pleased to have you
here and um looking forward to your
session titled PL ebo nosbo and
contextual effects the missing the
missed Link in clinical
practice over to
you thank you for the presentation and
for the invitation to use this talk it's
a pleasure for me to be here for the
hativ inference Symposium and today I
talk about clbo noo and contextual
effects showing the Mis Link in clinical
practice as I mentioned I'm an Italian
physical therapist I'm involved in
clinici in research and teaching session
I come from Verona that is a city in the
north of Italy and it represent the city
of love on Romeo and Juliet and if you
have never visited my suggestion is to
do
it before to start I want to declare
that I have no conflict of interest for
my
speech I Have organized my presentation
to discuss contexual effects firstly we
will analyze the definition and the
constituent dimensions of contextual
effects the mechanisms of action the
impact on outcomes and treatments next
we will discuss the possible link of
contextual effects with the active
inference and the implication for
clinical practice and research finally
we will conclude with a take on
message contextual effects are defined
as the effects of the context around the
therapy and are generated by contextual
factors contextual factors were recently
defined in international consensus in
which I participated in the slide you
will find an accept of the final share
definition where contextual effector are
the perceived views that affect both the
patient and the practitioner and can
arise from previous experiences and the
immediate Dynamics within the
therapeutic encounter or a combination
of
both and from a clinical perspective
contextual factors fall into five broad
categories or Dimensions that you can
see represented in this graph on one
hand we have the characteristic of the
clinicians with their professional
reputations the appearance the beliefs
and behaviors on the other side there
are the patients characteristic with
their expectations preferences and
previous experiences between the
clinicians and the patients there is the
relational Dynamics in terms of verbal
and nonverbal communication what we say
and how we
communicate in in addition to the
relational component the treatment
characteristics also play an important
role they represent the rituality of the
treatment
finally The Fifth Dimension is
represented by the characteristics of
the setting within which the encounter
is being delivered such as the
environment the architecture and also
the interior design well all these five
Dimensions interacting with each other
influence the overall therapeutic
outcomes the question we have to ask
ourself is through which mechanisms does
this happen I will tell you in the next
slides contextual Factor have been
studied for their ability to induce
Placebo and noo effects which represent
the effects of the psychosocial context
around the th and to explain how this
occurs I want to start with a clinical
example this illustration show a common
clinical encounter in which patients
with the muscular skial pain receive a
therapy such as joint
immobilization therapeutic exercises or
an ultrasound injections and during the
administration of therapy patients are
influenced by the specificity of the
treatment but also by various different
psychos social cues such as the
clinicians work the Sight and Sound of
the health care devices the smells of
the hygienic and also the taste of the
drugs when receiving for example a
painkillers well all these cues can
influence the patient's perception
shaping the experience in a positive or
in a negative way triggering Placebo or
nobo effects thus the positive use of
contextual factors can produce Placebo
effects when these elements are used
negatively it produce noo effects and
the clinical effects of contextual
factors can be explained through
conscious and unconscious mechanisms of
action such as expectation learning
processes personality traits mindset and
even if
genetics however among the most
important psychological theories
expectation classical conditioning and
social learning are the most widely
accepted the expectation is a conscious
phenomena through which the patient
expect that something will happen in the
Futures we need to consider patients for
example who are waiting to receive a
therapeutic exercises or manual therapy
for a muscular schal pain well they will
predict a positive therapeutic outcome
by evaluating all the contextual factors
around the therapy we offer as a
clinician such as our Worth or our
behaviors instead the classical pav of
condition is is an unconscious
phenomenon concerning the past events in
fact patients can learn over time to
associate a certain therapy such as for
example an inactions with a specific
context effects that represent the
rituality of the technique created by
the needles that produce a certain
outcome which can be positive or
negative but patients can also learn
from others they can learn from positive
or negative experiences of other
patients family members friends or from
information they get from social media
or blogs regarding for example muscular
skial pain but how the contextual Factor
Works in practice I will use this image
to explain this mechanisms of action
briefly whenever patient interact will
the healthcare context that are always
influenced by the five contential
factors and these elements are encoded
by the patient brain who interprets them
and provides an evaluation and a
prediction of their meaning and if this
interpretation is positive Place effects
are triggered if the interpretation is
negative noo effects are stimulated and
these effects are sustained by a Cascade
of a psychon immuno endocrinological
events at multiple level of the central
nervous systems in terms of the release
of
neurotransmitters for example negative
contextual factors can activate the
release of kyin and the deactivation of
dopamine and the opioid systems instead
the use of the positive Contex factors
can facilitate the release of a PES
endoc canids
andam and also different brain areas can
be activated for example the dorsal
lateral peral cortex the anterior
singulate cortex and the g per gray and
the dorsal Horn of the spine are
modulated and all these specific
neurological Pathways translated into
changes in clinical outcomes and using
for example muscul scal pain as an
example if the context oper is positive
the patients will perceive a relief of
symptoms instead if the Contex adopted
is negative the patient will have an
aggravation of symptoms and contexual
factors interacting with the treatment
specificity are able to influence more
the patient subjective outcomes or the
illness demensions than the objective
outcomes that represent the disease
component for example pain disability
experience satisfaction represent
typical example of outcomes influenced
by contextual factors however not all
the changes of the therapeutic outs are
due by contextual factors or by the
specificity of our treatment in fact
several Compounders can explain the
improvements or the worsening of the
patient clinical condition an example
are reported in this graph for example
the natural history of the disease can
explain the natural flation of the of
symtom or the regression towards the
means which represent a statistical
phenomena or for example the presence of
unidentified intervention as in the case
of patient that present a muscular schal
pain or receive a manual therapy or
therapeutic exercise and concomitantly
receive also a
painkillers another question we should
have ask ourself is what is the weight
of contextual factors influences the
outcome and for a long time it was a
common opinion in the scientific Comm
that about 33 to 4
35% of the total therapeutic effects
depend on the contextual component and
even if it me seem limited it is
actually not because it is a component
influencing clinical outcome that we
should know and we should use in our
clinical practice and the international
debate on the weight of contextual
effects has continued to the present day
without find the conclusion
several recent systematic reviews with
the with the metanalysis has assessed
the weight of contextual effects what
the different authors have observed is
that the contextual effects can vary
from small to large and I report here
different example you can see what
happen for no specific loic pain neck
pain fibromyalgia and also NEOS
arthritis and the heterogenity in these
results can be explained for example by
the characteristic of the patients the
clinicians by the characteristic of the
condition analyze the interventions
considered and also by the
characteristic of the statistical metric
adopted so some student has also
provided data on the contextual effects
for treatments for example in this meta
research the contextual effects of of
different treatments was evaluated and
what we can observe is that the
contextual is progressively higher in
treatment with the high ralistic Futures
to go into details in psychological
treatments the the contextual effects
account for the
38% in pharmacological treatments it
accounts for the
61% and in the physical treatment such
as manual therapy or handson techniques
it accounts for the 65%
64% and
having reached this point I think that
we need to understand how contextual
effects can be related to the theme of
this coner this conference the active
inference and to understand this we need
to start with a clinical example we need
to think about the management of
patients with persistent muscular skial
pain who have negative expectations
based on their previous experiences
psychological characteristics or
personality traits and for example if
you consider a patient with the neck
pain that in the past has been exposed
to exercises and learn that these
exercises produces pain consolidating a
negative internal model to worth this in
our patients Clinic we offer exercises
to our neck pain patients in accordance
with the best evidence and as a result
of this direct experience the patient
can have two main outcomes
at first for example it can confirm that
exercises can produce pain or the
patients may not perceive the pain
violated their
expectations and this violation of
expectation is interesting because it
can result in two main
scenarios one adapted IND where patients
Mak an it makes an update of their
expectation and on their internal model
and a d functional one where the
patients consider this violation as an
exception to the rule or as results to
the chance and therefore maintain it and
this is referred to as a cognitively
immuniz patients and we suggest that
such differen in updating responses can
be understood it at least to some extent
from a basian
perspectiv and in fact the ability to
make an update of the patient
expectation can be interpreted in the
light of the basian model and will
depend on the strength and accuracy of
the patient prior beliefs and behaviors
and from a biiian perspectives our brain
is conceptualizes a predictor machine
that generates predictions know as PRI
about the expected sensory inputs and
the integration between the prior and
the sensor inputs results in the
posterior the percept with which can be
more or less influenced by the prior and
by the sensory data depending on their
level of precision and let let us think
about the patients with the pain who has
negative prior or expectations toward
exercise they represented the sensory
input and if these priors are very
precise and
reliable it will be much more difficult
for the patient to rely on the sensory
input given by the exercises and the
prediction error is really minimal and
the patients consider the experience as
a result of a of the chance or an
exception of the rule existing in
maintainance or the initial
expectations instead if the
interpretation are less precise and
reliable it will be much easier for the
patients to rely on the sensor inputs
given by the exercise because the
prediction error between what it is
expected and what it is experienced will
be more significant will contribute to
improving the patient expectation by
generating update and I think is very
fascinating and complex but it does alls
us to think about how we can use the
context to challenge or Mak an updates
of the patients prior and I will try to
help you to understand this point with
another clinical
example with this B model in mind it is
possible to better understand the
clinical scenario presented in this
image where we have the patients with
the muscul schal pain of the shoulder
has had a negative
PR in that in that situation the
patients prefer not to rise their harms
because they have been told that the
tendons can stop on the other hand we
have the clinicians who tries to
challenge the patients prior through the
tools that he has disposal for example
the exercises the manal therapy the
virtual reality and the education but
the clinician also has another secret
weapon to use that this schol has the
contextual factors made by words cues
behaviors rituality that can influence
the patient's brain and the patients
prior and as an outcome of this
challenge we can have for example
expectation violation following by an
update which is realized when the prior
with low Precision of our patient is
updated accordingly with the newly
acquired evidence the patients leave the
bre the arms without any pain and
without any types of
lesions another possible scenario is
represented by the expectation violation
followed by the maintainance of the
dysfunctional beliefs as the consequence
of one having a highly puru prior which
is considered really reliable and
therefore the newly acquired information
and this confirmatory evidence is not
sufficient to disprove and update the
such strong prior and for example in
this case we have a patient with a
muscular cical pain that during a
clinical section manage to leave their
har without any negative consequences to
their shoulder but still believe that
leing the arm will possible create and
lead to the shoulder to break are likely
to have for example a very high precise
prior and might discard the positive
evidence for example the sucess in
lifting the har which might might be
classified as an exception instead of
the
rule so try to pull the string of the
speech what might be the implication for
this uh from this talk to our clinical
practice the use of contextual factors
represent an opportunity to Aras the
evidence based therapy we know it as a
clinician but as a clinician we also
need to consider that using context of
factors such as words touch the
rituality of the technique and
environment could help to challenge the
patients prior and improve the patient
muscular Cal pain however this
observation that arise from the clinic
need to be supported by data and more
study to substantiate their
effectiveness thus researchers are
called up to integrate contextual
effects into the study on muscal pain
using for example the basian brain and
the active inference lens and to do is
this it is important to produce
experimental work in the lab in the
click work in patient to validate these
theoretical models by using for example
subjective outcomes but also some
objective physiological
metrics we are in the end so I concluded
I want to cre in you wishing you to
remain curious clinicians capable to see
the things from different perspective
and asset the complexity presented in
the clinic and also within this image
let's not just focus only on the details
the te the technique it is important but
it is not all let us always remember
that the scenario in which we operate it
is much more complex and both the
context the moon and the confounders The
Surge and the sky comes into play only
if we Embrace this opportunity and this
complexity we could find new strategy to
best manage our patients with muscular
skial pain thanks for your
attentions thank you
thank you till next time